<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Holistic Health | Hunor Becsi&#39;s Website</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/en/tags/holistic-health/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/en/tags/holistic-health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Holistic Health</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu7729264130191091259.png</url>
      <title>Holistic Health</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/tags/holistic-health/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why I Write About Health Topics as an Everyday Person?</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/post/whyipublishhealth/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/post/whyipublishhealth/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;why-i-blog-about-health-topics-a-journey-of-discovery&#34;&gt;Why I Blog About Health Topics: A Journey of Discovery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In today&amp;rsquo;s complex health care environment, confusion and misinformation often lead individuals to seek quick fixes that may compromise their well-being. It is essential to recognise that the incentives driving health information can range from altruistic public health initiatives to self-serving profit motives. These incentives run a wide spectrum and reflect different motivations that can influence health decisions. Public health professionals and institutions often work for the benefit of the people and are committed to promoting the health of the community. In contrast, market actors seeking profit often manipulate information to serve their own interests while ignoring the real needs of patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My aim in this blog is not to dismiss the efficacy of well-established medical treatments backed by empirical evidence, nor to criticise the entire medical establishment. However, it is obvious that I will criticise those points that may be detrimental to us. Given the various incentives and interests involved, it is essential that we take a critical approach to the health information we consume. My reflections are drawn from personal experience and research and highlight the importance of being cautious about the health advice we take. Only then can we ensure that our choices are informed and make a real contribution to our long-term health. Understanding the source of information and the motivations behind it is key to avoiding wrong paths and potential dangers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both traditional and alternative medical guidance can sometimes be tainted by misinformation, half-truths, or hidden agendas influenced by various entities, including medical institutions and profit-driven companies. This can lead to conflicts of interest where financial gain overshadows patient well-being. As consumers become more informed, the demand for transparency in health information increases, yet fear-based marketing and regulatory capture can further complicate our decision-making.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through this blog, I aim to share my insights and findings to empower readers, broaden their perspectives, and encourage critical thinking. By fostering a culture of inquiry and skepticism, we can navigate the health landscape with confidence, making informed decisions that genuinely serve our best interests. Understanding our bodies and health is crucial, regardless of our professional backgrounds, and I hope to facilitate a journey of discovery that enhances our overall well-being. Together, let us embark on this path, prioritizing health and fostering trust in the information we encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Importance of Understanding Health&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is concerning to observe that people from all walks of life-whether wealthy celebrities or those deemed less significant-suffer from preventable health issues. This suggests a fundamental gap in our understanding of health and wellness. Many could lead healthier lives if they were educated on the basics of bodily functions and nutrition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prominent historian Yuval Noah Harari once remarked, “Humans typically learn to manipulate something long before they understand the consequences of their manipulations.” This applies not only to our environment but also to our own bodies. It is crucial that we comprehend the implications of our dietary choices and lifestyle habits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;personal-experiences-and-observations&#34;&gt;Personal Experiences and Observations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, in my personal experience consulting medical professionals here in Hungary, I found that they were often uncertain about the connection between skin tags and moles and insulin resistance. I am not implying that such connections do not exist; rather, I have yet to meet a practitioner who has confirmed this link. However, several health practitioners, including licensed medical doctors, have pointed out a relationship between these skin conditions and metabolic issues. Research studies, including at least &lt;a href=&#34;https://pmc.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/articles/PMC6536054/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;one&lt;/a&gt;, linking skin tags to metabolic syndrome, suggest that skin tags may serve as visible markers of underlying metabolic issues, particularly insulin resistance. This underscores the importance of monitoring individuals with skin tags for potential metabolic disturbances, which can inform better healthcare practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conflicting information available can create confusion and frustration for individuals facing these differing views. They may feel uncertain about their health and the validity of the advice they receive, leading to anxiety over potential underlying health issues. The lack of a clear consensus can cause them to second-guess their treatment options or hesitate to seek further medical advice. This internal conflict may result in feelings of helplessness as they strive to comprehend their condition amidst contradictory perspectives. Ultimately, this situation could hinder their ability to make informed decisions regarding their health and well-being, potentially delaying necessary interventions or lifestyle changes that could improve their overall condition. Despite emerging evidence, many healthcare providers may remain unaware of such connections, and there can be some resistance to acknowledging them, which can sometimes lead to misunderstandings about differing perspectives in the medical community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To illustrate this point, consider &lt;strong&gt;an intriguing conversation posted on YouTube between Dr. Ken D. Berry and Dr. Robert Lufkin titled &amp;ldquo;Why Your Doctor Lies to You&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;video-wrapper&#34; data-video-id=&#34;ZkkbwA7We2U&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img 
    src=&#34;https://img.youtube.com/vi/ZkkbwA7We2U/hqdefault.jpg&#34; 
    alt=&#34;Video Thumbnail&#34; 
    loading=&#34;lazy&#34; 
    class=&#34;video-thumbnail&#34; 
  /&gt;
  &lt;button class=&#34;play-button&#34; aria-label=&#34;Play&#34;&gt;
    
    
    
    &lt;svg width=&#34;40&#34; height=&#34;40&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 24 24&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34; xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34;&gt;
      &lt;circle cx=&#34;12&#34; cy=&#34;12&#34; r=&#34;10&#34; fill=&#34;rgba(0,0,0,0.6)&#34; /&gt;
      &lt;polygon points=&#34;10,8 16,12 10,16&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/svg&gt;
  &lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  document.addEventListener(&#39;DOMContentLoaded&#39;, () =&gt; {
    document.querySelectorAll(&#39;.video-wrapper&#39;).forEach(wrapper =&gt; {
      wrapper.querySelector(&#39;.play-button&#39;).addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, () =&gt; {
        const videoId = wrapper.dataset.videoId;
        const iframe = document.createElement(&#39;iframe&#39;);
        iframe.src = `https://www.youtube.com/embed/${videoId}?autoplay=1`;
        iframe.width = &#34;560&#34;;
        iframe.height = &#34;315&#34;;
        iframe.allowFullscreen = true;
        iframe.setAttribute(&#39;loading&#39;, &#39;lazy&#39;);
        wrapper.innerHTML = &#39;&#39;;
        wrapper.appendChild(iframe);
      });
    });
  });
&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Both individuals discussed changes related to their own health that led them to reevaluate their perspectives on medicine and certain medical practices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Brief summary from 38:33 minutes into the conversation:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Ken D. Berry:&lt;/strong&gt;
&amp;ldquo;One thing that I found for the average person-whether they&amp;rsquo;re a waitress, a truck driver, or work at a big box store-is that they tend to look up to doctors and healthcare professionals. It&amp;rsquo;s ingrained in us. They perceive these individuals as smarter than themselves. The truth is that these professionals have simply been in school longer than most and possess in-depth knowledge about a very narrow subject. It&amp;rsquo;s human nature to look up to an expert; we can’t help it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the average person hears us talking about corruption-both the blatant fraud and what I term &amp;lsquo;soft blackmail&amp;rsquo;-it can be shocking. I&amp;rsquo;m not suggesting outright bribery, but rather subtle pressures like, &amp;lsquo;We would love for this study to have favorable outcomes because we want to fund a new residency program and name it after you.&amp;rsquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a professor in medical school, I want to help those outside of academia understand that doctors are just &amp;ldquo;dudes and chicks&amp;rdquo;. They are not demigods. They are not inherently more ethical or moral; they are just as susceptible to logical fallacies and the pressures that come with funding.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr. Robert Lufkin:&lt;/strong&gt;
&amp;ldquo;Absolutely, Ken. That&amp;rsquo;s so true! Those in the field, while well-meaning, are influenced by subconscious factors. When they attended medical school, whether five years ago or 20, that’s when their foundational knowledge was established. As they specialize-Family Medicine itself is a specialty-they become immersed in the knowledge and biases of that specialty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s critical to recognize that these healthcare professionals are just &amp;ldquo;dudes and chicks&amp;rdquo; trying to navigate their jobs, make mortgage payments, and care for their families while also attending to patients. However, at the end of the day, the one person who knows me best is myself. I may not hold a medical degree, but I understand my life experiences and lifestyle choices better than any doctor can glean from a few brief visits.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Conclusion:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to understand that even the most well-meaning doctors or scientists can sometimes mislead others without intending to do so. Yet, it is crucial to avoid broad generalizations. Both compassionate and misguided individuals can contribute to confusion, and this complexity is an intrinsic part of the human experience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;challenges-in-modern-medicine&#34;&gt;Challenges in Modern Medicine&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Alt text&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/whyipublishhealth/post/whyipublishhealth/challenges_hu4894072140575017218.webp 400w,
               /en/post/whyipublishhealth/post/whyipublishhealth/challenges_hu7956779682345107758.webp 760w,
               /en/post/whyipublishhealth/post/whyipublishhealth/challenges_hu5519391483824994954.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/en/post/whyipublishhealth/post/whyipublishhealth/challenges_hu4894072140575017218.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While personal journeys can provide insight, they often highlight broader challenges within the medical community. Recently, I encountered a troubling trend when a respected healthcare professional dismissed discussions about alternative health practices simply because they contradicted mainstream advice. This incident underscores a significant issue: a rigid adherence to traditional methods that often overlooks emerging evidence challenging the status quo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. Fragmentation of Care:&lt;/strong&gt;
Many individuals, myself included, have successfully reversed conditions such as high blood pressure, complicated aura-type migraines, and obesity through lifestyle changes rather than relying solely on medications. However, the fragmentation inherent in Western medical practices can lead to a lack of holistic understanding and coordination in patient care. Navigating multiple specialists often results in conflicting treatment plans that overlook the broader context of the patient’s health, which I have experienced firsthand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. Reliance on Protocols:&lt;/strong&gt;
This reliance on standardized treatment regimens can hinder the ability to tailor treatments to meet the unique needs of each patient. I often feel that some medical professionals lack a comprehensive understanding of holistic health and nutrition. During one examination, a doctor even suggested that I should stop researching health topics and leave them to the professionals. Such a short-sighted attitude reflects a reluctance to embrace the growing body of evidence supporting lifestyle interventions and patient empowerment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. Pharmaceutical Influence:&lt;/strong&gt;
The influence of the pharmaceutical industry on healthcare practice is a major concern that needs careful consideration. Many healthcare providers often rely heavily on medicines as the primary solution to a variety of health problems. This tendency can lead to a limited focus that overlooks root causes or alternative interventions, perpetuating a cycle of drug dependence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dependence on medicines can obscure the treatment of the root causes of health problems, which are often rooted in lifestyle factors such as diet, exercise and mental health. Research shows that many chronic diseases, including autoimmune diseases, can be significantly managed or even reversed through strategic lifestyle changes, particularly through proper nutrition. For example, studies have shown that individuals with autoimmune diseases who switched to a rich, anti-inflammatory, whole-food diet experienced significant symptom relief and improved quality of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To better illustrate this concept, let&amp;rsquo;s compare the health of our bodies to a beautiful but very complex piece of music, where drugs, nutrition and other environmental influences represent a multi-channel sound mixer. Each channel represents a different function or system in our bodies, with different switches and sliders that need to be finely tuned to achieve harmony.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we use drugs, we are essentially adjusting one of the sliders - this may enhance or restrict a particular bodily function, but it does not address the underlying problems that are causing the dysfunction. The mixer can modify the sound of the music, but the errors in the musical composition need to be corrected by the music itself, not just by the mixer. To achieve a truly lasting and harmonious result, the source must be corrected, the composition must be refined, so that the music stands on its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now imagine a scenario where you add several remedies in succession. Each drug has its own side effects and interactions. If these interventions are carried out without addressing the root cause of the disorder, we risk creating a cacophony of symptoms instead of a symphony of health. Just as a sound mixer can create chaos if the channels are not properly balanced, your health can deteriorate if you rely solely on medication and do not make lifestyle changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a symphony of our health, the music reminds us that to create a harmonious harmony of sound, it is not enough to highlight the notes of a single instrument; we must consider the whole composition to make the music truly expressive and lasting. Ultimately, although medicines can play a significant role in the management of symptoms, they should not overshadow the importance of holistic approaches to health. By prioritising lifestyle changes and seeking to understand the root causes of health problems, individuals can develop a more balanced and sustainable relationship with their bodies, leading to better outcomes and overall wellbeing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is important to approach health as a multi-faceted journey that includes both medical and lifestyle interventions, ensuring that we are not just treating symptoms but nourishing the body towards optimal function and resilience. With this approach, the music and our health become a harmonious whole, with medicines merely acting as a mixer, while the real improvement lies in refining the music.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;4. Lack of Nutritional Understanding:&lt;/strong&gt;
The apparent correlation between modern diet and the rise of chronic diseases warrants further examination, particularly in light of the inadequate emphasis on nutrition within the medical community. As chronic diseases such as obesity, diabetes, and heart disease continue to escalate, it becomes increasingly clear that the food choices available and promoted in contemporary society may play a significant role in this trend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The modern diet, characterized by high levels of processed foods, added sugars, and unhealthy fats, contrasts sharply with the diets of our ancestors, who consumed whole, unprocessed foods that were rich in nutrients. Evidence suggests that the rise in chronic diseases parallels the shift toward these processed diets, which are often high in calories but low in essential nutrients. For instance, studies have shown that increased consumption of ultra-processed foods is linked to higher risks of obesity and metabolic disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the emphasis on frequent snacking and eating multiple times a day, as recommended by some dietitians, may inadvertently encourage the consumption of these unhealthy, processed options. This approach often overlooks the benefits of intermittent fasting or reduced meal frequency, which may align more closely with our ancestral eating patterns and support metabolic health. Historical diets were not only shaped by the availability of food but also by natural hunger cues, which allowed for periods of fasting that can promote cellular repair and improve insulin sensitivity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, the medical community&amp;rsquo;s reluctance to address these dietary changes-often opting for pharmacological solutions instead-contributes to a cycle where patients remain unaware of the profound impact that nutrition can have on their health. By not prioritizing nutritional education or integrating it into patient care, healthcare providers may inadvertently perpetuate the rise of chronic diseases, leaving patients confused and misled about effective dietary strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the disconnect between modern dietary recommendations and historical eating practices, coupled with a lack of nutritional emphasis in medical care, presents a compelling case for re-evaluating our approach to nutrition. By fostering a greater understanding of how our diets influence health, we can empower individuals to make informed choices that prioritize whole foods and minimize processed options, potentially curbing the rise of chronic diseases and promoting overall well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;5. Patient Responsibility and Mindset:&lt;/strong&gt;
The importance of patient agency in the healing process cannot be overstated. While medical professionals play a crucial role, patients must confront their own habits and lifestyle choices to achieve lasting health improvements. True healing requires significant personal commitment and a willingness to change-not only in diet but also in mental outlook. Many patients may prefer the convenience of medication over the effort required for substantial lifestyle changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our pursuit of comfort and convenience, we often overlook a critical aspect of our health: &lt;strong&gt;the resilience of our bodies&lt;/strong&gt;. Human beings have been designed to withstand a variety of harsh environmental factors-be it extreme temperatures, physical exertion, or dietary scarcity. By excessively prioritizing comfort, we risk becoming negligent of our body&amp;rsquo;s innate capabilities and needs. This reliance on convenience can lead to a sedentary lifestyle, poor dietary choices, and mental stagnation, ultimately undermining our health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, maintaining our body&amp;rsquo;s resilience is not just about protecting ourselves against external environmental factors, but also about consciously training and developing these abilities. The principle of ‘use it or lose it’ is fundamental to this issue. It&amp;rsquo;s not for nothing that doctors and health professionals stress this fact: if we don&amp;rsquo;t make regular use of our body&amp;rsquo;s different abilities, we can lose them over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, a lack of physical activity quickly leads to a weakening of our muscles and bones, which in the long term reduces our resistance to injury and disease. One study shows that older people who exercise regularly are less prone to osteoporosis and inflammatory diseases because they maintain these bodily functions. Likewise, regular exercise improves cardiovascular health, increases lung capacity and strengthens the immune system - all of which are skills that can only be maintained if they are used regularly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The same applies to the immune system: if we do not “train” properly, i.e. keep our immune responses active, we can reduce our body&amp;rsquo;s defences. For example, excessive hygiene and social isolation have been linked to the development of autism and allergic diseases, as the body does not get enough opportunity to develop its natural defence mechanisms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our body&amp;rsquo;s resilience is therefore not just a matter of genetics, but a system that is constantly maintained and developed. Regular physical activity, a healthy diet and mental challenges all contribute to our body&amp;rsquo;s ability to adapt to changing conditions, resist disease and recover quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary: to maintain our health and resilience in the long term, we need to be conscious of the “use it or lose it” principle. This means that we should not neglect regular exercise, proper nutrition and an active lifestyle, as these factors directly affect our body&amp;rsquo;s ability to resist external and internal challenges. Only in this way can we maintain our physical and mental health and ensure that our body&amp;rsquo;s resilience remains intact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The culprits in this equation are of course multi-faceted: the allure of modern technology, the abundance of processed foods, and societal norms that prioritize ease over effort. Yet, this tradeoff for comfort comes at a cost. By seeking to avoid discomfort, we may inadvertently compromise our physical and mental well-being. Embracing challenges, whether through physical activity or mindful eating, can foster resilience and contribute to a more robust health foundation. In recognizing this delicate balance, patients can reclaim their agency and make informed choices that promote not only healing but also a more fulfilled and resilient life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;6. Challenges in Patient-Provider Communication:&lt;/strong&gt;
Communication barriers between patients and healthcare providers can hinder effective treatment plans. Instances of skepticism or dismissal regarding collaborative approaches can stifle innovative therapies that may benefit patients. I have encountered dismissal from some family members, even some friends, but mostly from doctors who view my experience as merely anecdotal, despite my remarkable improvements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;7. The Role of Education and Awareness:&lt;/strong&gt;
The need for greater education and awareness about nutrition and holistic health among both patients and healthcare professionals is critical. Articles warning against &amp;ldquo;internet medicine&amp;rdquo; caution that it can lead to anxiety, but I have found it a valuable tool for gathering information, connecting with communities, and discovering potential avenues for research that traditional medical consultations might overlook.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am genuinely concerned when medical practitioners hastily recommend surgical interventions, such as gallbladder removal, without thoroughly exploring less invasive alternatives. Research indicates that many gallbladder-related issues, including gallstones, can often be effectively managed through lifestyle changes and dietary adjustments. For instance, studies have shown that diets low in refined carbohydrates and rich in fiber significantly reduce the risk of gallstone formation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The gallbladder plays an essential role in fat digestion by concentrating and releasing bile, necessary for the emulsification and absorption of dietary fats-key macronutrients vital for overall health. Once the gallbladder is removed, patients may struggle with efficient fat digestion, potentially leading to long-term complications such as diarrhea or malabsorption of vital fat-soluble vitamins. The emphasis on collaborative care between patients and healthcare providers is increasingly supported by evidence in the field of patient-centered medicine, fostering a sense of ownership over health decisions, leading to better adherence to treatment plans and improved outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8. Caution with Alternative Practices:&lt;/strong&gt;
While it is crucial to advocate for alternative practices, a balanced view must also address the potential risks associated with these methods. Even when a practice or treatment appears to be based on sound science, it is essential to carefully assess both the benefits and the possible negative effects. For instance, some individuals may turn to unverified online resources that promote certain diets or treatments without considering their individual health needs or the potential for adverse effects. A deeper exploration of the safety concerns surrounding alternative practices is necessary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, following a ketogenic diet can lead to negative side effects, such as &amp;ldquo;keto flu,&amp;rdquo; which are often highlighted by those opposing the diet. However, these fear-inducing &amp;ldquo;experts&amp;rdquo; often fail to mention that these symptoms are a natural part of the body&amp;rsquo;s adaptation to changes in diet. With proper knowledge, the transition to a healthy ketogenic diet can be made without these adverse effects or, at the very least, significantly minimized. Personally, aside from some headaches that were alleviated by consuming salt, I did not experience a &amp;ldquo;rough ride&amp;rdquo; into ketosis. While ketosis is a metabolic process that is beneficial for many individuals, the ketogenic diet itself is not necessarily suitable for everyone. Women, in particular, may need to avoid it, especially before their period, due to their unique physiology and hormonal makeup, which differ from men&amp;rsquo;s. There are many more considerations that will only become apparent if one actively seeks them out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ketogenic diet can be implemented using both healthy and unhealthy food sources. Ketosis itself does not equate to good health, and there is much more to understand about it. Even as an enthusiastic researcher on the topic, I recognize that I still have much to learn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I will be the first to say: do not accept an alternative practice unless you have adequately researched it, consulted with multiple medical professionals, and examined the evidence behind such a practice or treatment. Just because something is presented as a viable option does not mean it is free from risks. Unfortunately, you yourself will bear the risks of any choices made, which is all the more reason to not take such decisions lightly. One guideline I frequently see is to never pay upfront for any &amp;ldquo;miracle diet or treatment&amp;rdquo; without thoroughly understanding all aspects of it. What sounds too good to be true or too easy is often not the truth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If data or facts are not readily available, or if the &amp;ldquo;medical expert&amp;rdquo; does not share them openly and you cannot cross-check with other sources, you might be misled into a potentially dangerous venture. It is imperative to remain vigilant and discerning, recognizing that even seemingly credible practices can lead to unintended consequences. In the pursuit of health and wellness, prioritizing informed decision-making and evidence-based practices should always be at the forefront.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;personal-anecdotes-and-broader-insights&#34;&gt;Personal Anecdotes and Broader Insights:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Alt text&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/whyipublishhealth/post/whyipublishhealth/personal_hu10026104888645799595.webp 400w,
               /en/post/whyipublishhealth/post/whyipublishhealth/personal_hu6755017231154668417.webp 760w,
               /en/post/whyipublishhealth/post/whyipublishhealth/personal_hu1566835556559402931.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/en/post/whyipublishhealth/post/whyipublishhealth/personal_hu10026104888645799595.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The movie &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First Do No Harm (1997)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt; (&lt;a href=&#34;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22575229/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pubmed article related to true stories behind&lt;/a&gt;) tells the poignant true story of a mother named Lori, whose son, Robbie, suffers from severe intractable epilepsy. Lori&amp;rsquo;s journey reflects the struggles of many families facing similar medical challenges, and her real-life counterpart, Phyllis Abrahams, exemplifies the resilience and determination required to navigate a complex healthcare system. Interestingly, I have also experienced a similar journey, having been falsely diagnosed with epilepsy during my childhood in Romania. This misdiagnosis led to a challenging medical experience, including a procedure called pneumoencephalography, which involved injecting air into the cerebrospinal fluid (CSF) to improve imaging for conditions like epilepsy. Unfortunately, this risky procedure could have resulted in serious complications, such as infections and seizures. On top of that, I was prescribed epilepsy medications as well. Ultimately, in my early teens, a neurologist diagnosed me with severe migraines-potentially caused by the pneumoencephalography or the antiepileptic drugs-and confirmed that I never actually had epilepsy; I was merely sleepwalking. Coming to terms with the fact that I had undergone such a dangerous practice based on an incorrect diagnosis was difficult.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As Lori, inspired by Phyllis&amp;rsquo;s relentless search for solutions, explored alternative options for her son after exhausting traditional medical avenues, I too found myself seeking similar paths following struggles with aura migraines, high blood pressure, obesity, and the likely underlying cause: insulin resistance. Lori&amp;rsquo;s research into dietary changes, particularly the ketogenic diet, dramatically reduced her son’s seizures, illustrating a mother’s unwavering commitment to her child&amp;rsquo;s health. Likewise, my exploration of a ketogenic lifestyle has significantly improved my health, allowing me to reclaim my well-being.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both Lori’s experience and mine underscore the critical need for the medical community to heed patients&amp;rsquo; voices and consider alternative treatments. Just as Lori faced skepticism regarding her unconventional approach, I too have encountered dismissal from some healthcare providers despite achieving remarkable health improvements. This raises an important question: How many personal accounts must accumulate before the medical community acknowledges and embraces these insights?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is substantial literature by health professionals and investigative journalists-such as Gary Taubes, author of The Case Against Sugar and The Case for Keto, and Dr. Robert Lustig, author of Metabolical-demonstrating how dietary changes can improve health outcomes. While this article cannot delve into all available research, it emphasizes the need for further exploration and dialogue around these dietary approaches. Personal anecdotes, like Lori’s and mine, can serve as a gateway to understanding how different diets may affect individual well-being; however, it is essential to approach these topics with an open mind and a critical eye. What works for one person may not yield the same results for another, and engaging with healthcare professionals while staying informed about ongoing research can aid individuals in making informed health decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While surgical interventions and medication are justified in acute situations, the medical community should prioritize a holistic approach that includes dietary counseling and less invasive options. By fostering open dialogue and mutual respect between patients and healthcare providers, we can bridge the gap between conventional medicine and alternative practices, enhancing the quality of care and improving health outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding the full potential of alternative health practices is fraught with obstacles, but addressing these challenges is essential for advancing our collective knowledge. The future of healthcare necessitates an integrated approach that values both scientific evidence and patient experiences. In a landscape where funding for comprehensive research is limited and long-term studies pose significant challenges, it is imperative to remain vigilant and discerning. Critically examining alternative practices and prioritizing informed decision-making should always be at the forefront of our health journeys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-importance-of-health-literacy&#34;&gt;The Importance of Health Literacy&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;Alt text&#34; srcset=&#34;
               /en/post/whyipublishhealth/post/whyipublishhealth/literacy_hu17455892808100825364.webp 400w,
               /en/post/whyipublishhealth/post/whyipublishhealth/literacy_hu4438179741086683099.webp 760w,
               /en/post/whyipublishhealth/post/whyipublishhealth/literacy_hu12619285027255958782.webp 1200w&#34;
               src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/en/post/whyipublishhealth/post/whyipublishhealth/literacy_hu17455892808100825364.webp&#34;
               width=&#34;760&#34;
               height=&#34;507&#34;
               loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Health literacy is a crucial component of navigating the complex world of healthcare. As individuals become more informed about health topics, they empower themselves to make better decisions regarding their well-being. However, as we enhance our health literacy, it is vital to remain vigilant about the biases that can permeate the medical community. Medical professionals often operate within established protocols, which can inadvertently stifle innovative or alternative approaches to treatment. Some professionals may feel pressured to adhere to these established protocols, fearing repercussions for exploring alternative approaches. There is a delicate balance between adhering to proven methods and being open to novel ideas that may enhance patient care.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My personal journey through various health topics has underscored the profound impact that nutrition can have on overall health, even if it cannot cure specific diseases like cancer. Experts in the field advocate for the integration of current medical treatments with improved dietary practices, yet this holistic view frequently encounters resistance. Such opposition may stem from a reluctance to deviate from traditional practices or a fear of undermining established medical protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is essential to understand that while many healthcare professionals dedicate their lives to rigorous research and specialization, there are inherent risks in maintaining a narrow focus. This “tunnel vision” can limit their ability to consider broader perspectives, which is critical in an ever-evolving field like healthcare. Embracing a multidisciplinary approach allows for a more comprehensive understanding of health issues, fostering innovation and better outcomes for patients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have immense respect for those who engage in deep research; their contributions are invaluable to the advancement of medical knowledge. However, it is crucial that the findings from such research are not viewed in isolation. They should be subject to scrutiny and consideration from a wider context, allowing for a more inclusive understanding of health and wellness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite my limited knowledge and experience, I recognize that my insights are just a small piece of a much larger puzzle. This awareness compels me to approach health literacy with humility, acknowledging that our understanding of health is not static but rather an evolving journey. As we quest for knowledge and truth, we must remain open to new ideas and perspectives, understanding that our current beliefs may one day transform in light of new evidence or shifts in societal values. This ongoing exploration is not only vital for personal growth but also essential for the collective advancement of health literacy in a rapidly changing world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;taking-responsibility-for-our-health&#34;&gt;Taking Responsibility for Our Health&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the responsibility for our health lies with us as individuals. We must diligently research our health options and understand the implications of our choices. While medications and surgeries can be life-saving, relying solely on them without understanding the underlying causes of our ailments can lead to further complications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I acknowledge that there are health situations where invasive surgery or medication may be necessary to save a life, at least in the short term. However, I believe we must also consider the quality of life after such interventions. Some conditions can lead individuals to wish they had not survived, facing serious impairments that diminish their quality of life. This is a profound consideration for anyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a wise friend once said, &amp;ldquo;Living itself is dangerous - you could die at any time!&amp;rdquo; Each day presents myriad risks, and while we can strive to minimize them, we cannot create contingency plans for every potential outcome. This fear often leads to a mindset I find difficult to comprehend in today&amp;rsquo;s society, which greatly influences the efforts of the medical establishment as well. Embracing a more open-minded approach to health that incorporates both traditional and alternative methods may empower individuals to take charge of their well-being rather than confining them to rigid paradigms. Ultimately, the goal should be to facilitate informed choices, allowing patients to navigate the complexities of healthcare with a broader understanding of their options.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;goal-and-takeaway&#34;&gt;Goal and Takeaway&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In sharing my journey and insights, I aim to empower you to take control of your health. By understanding our bodies and making informed choices, we can achieve better health outcomes. I invite you to explore the findings from my blog articles on my website, which reflect my research into various health topics. Remember, your health is your responsibility, and gaining knowledge about it is the first step toward a healthier life. If my conclusions resonate with you, I encourage you to embrace them; if they don&amp;rsquo;t, I respect your viewpoint. Ultimately, my goal is to inspire you to seek knowledge on your own health journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-closer-examination-of-the-inspiring-materials-behind-this-article&#34;&gt;A Closer Examination of the Inspiring Materials Behind This Article:&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;if-youre-curious-to-learn-more-i-encourage-you-to-dive-deeper-into-the-subject-by-exploring-additional-resources-and-perspectives-that-can-enrich-your-understanding&#34;&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re curious to learn more, I encourage you to dive deeper into the subject by exploring additional resources and perspectives that can enrich your understanding.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;youtube-videos&#34;&gt;YouTube Videos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;video-wrapper&#34; data-video-id=&#34;7STAPF4Gdr0&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img 
    src=&#34;https://img.youtube.com/vi/7STAPF4Gdr0/hqdefault.jpg&#34; 
    alt=&#34;Video Thumbnail&#34; 
    loading=&#34;lazy&#34; 
    class=&#34;video-thumbnail&#34; 
  /&gt;
  &lt;button class=&#34;play-button&#34; aria-label=&#34;Play&#34;&gt;
    
    
    
    &lt;svg width=&#34;40&#34; height=&#34;40&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 24 24&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34; xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34;&gt;
      &lt;circle cx=&#34;12&#34; cy=&#34;12&#34; r=&#34;10&#34; fill=&#34;rgba(0,0,0,0.6)&#34; /&gt;
      &lt;polygon points=&#34;10,8 16,12 10,16&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/svg&gt;
  &lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  document.addEventListener(&#39;DOMContentLoaded&#39;, () =&gt; {
    document.querySelectorAll(&#39;.video-wrapper&#39;).forEach(wrapper =&gt; {
      wrapper.querySelector(&#39;.play-button&#39;).addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, () =&gt; {
        const videoId = wrapper.dataset.videoId;
        const iframe = document.createElement(&#39;iframe&#39;);
        iframe.src = `https://www.youtube.com/embed/${videoId}?autoplay=1`;
        iframe.width = &#34;560&#34;;
        iframe.height = &#34;315&#34;;
        iframe.allowFullscreen = true;
        iframe.setAttribute(&#39;loading&#39;, &#39;lazy&#39;);
        wrapper.innerHTML = &#39;&#39;;
        wrapper.appendChild(iframe);
      });
    });
  });
&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;video-wrapper&#34; data-video-id=&#34;8AqlZK2TxZA&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img 
    src=&#34;https://img.youtube.com/vi/8AqlZK2TxZA/hqdefault.jpg&#34; 
    alt=&#34;Video Thumbnail&#34; 
    loading=&#34;lazy&#34; 
    class=&#34;video-thumbnail&#34; 
  /&gt;
  &lt;button class=&#34;play-button&#34; aria-label=&#34;Play&#34;&gt;
    
    
    
    &lt;svg width=&#34;40&#34; height=&#34;40&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 24 24&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34; xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34;&gt;
      &lt;circle cx=&#34;12&#34; cy=&#34;12&#34; r=&#34;10&#34; fill=&#34;rgba(0,0,0,0.6)&#34; /&gt;
      &lt;polygon points=&#34;10,8 16,12 10,16&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/svg&gt;
  &lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  document.addEventListener(&#39;DOMContentLoaded&#39;, () =&gt; {
    document.querySelectorAll(&#39;.video-wrapper&#39;).forEach(wrapper =&gt; {
      wrapper.querySelector(&#39;.play-button&#39;).addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, () =&gt; {
        const videoId = wrapper.dataset.videoId;
        const iframe = document.createElement(&#39;iframe&#39;);
        iframe.src = `https://www.youtube.com/embed/${videoId}?autoplay=1`;
        iframe.width = &#34;560&#34;;
        iframe.height = &#34;315&#34;;
        iframe.allowFullscreen = true;
        iframe.setAttribute(&#39;loading&#39;, &#39;lazy&#39;);
        wrapper.innerHTML = &#39;&#39;;
        wrapper.appendChild(iframe);
      });
    });
  });
&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;These videos address the relationship between skin tags and insulin resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;video-wrapper&#34; data-video-id=&#34;Oh5wT4r2EYA&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img 
    src=&#34;https://img.youtube.com/vi/Oh5wT4r2EYA/hqdefault.jpg&#34; 
    alt=&#34;Video Thumbnail&#34; 
    loading=&#34;lazy&#34; 
    class=&#34;video-thumbnail&#34; 
  /&gt;
  &lt;button class=&#34;play-button&#34; aria-label=&#34;Play&#34;&gt;
    
    
    
    &lt;svg width=&#34;40&#34; height=&#34;40&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 24 24&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34; xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34;&gt;
      &lt;circle cx=&#34;12&#34; cy=&#34;12&#34; r=&#34;10&#34; fill=&#34;rgba(0,0,0,0.6)&#34; /&gt;
      &lt;polygon points=&#34;10,8 16,12 10,16&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/svg&gt;
  &lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  document.addEventListener(&#39;DOMContentLoaded&#39;, () =&gt; {
    document.querySelectorAll(&#39;.video-wrapper&#39;).forEach(wrapper =&gt; {
      wrapper.querySelector(&#39;.play-button&#39;).addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, () =&gt; {
        const videoId = wrapper.dataset.videoId;
        const iframe = document.createElement(&#39;iframe&#39;);
        iframe.src = `https://www.youtube.com/embed/${videoId}?autoplay=1`;
        iframe.width = &#34;560&#34;;
        iframe.height = &#34;315&#34;;
        iframe.allowFullscreen = true;
        iframe.setAttribute(&#39;loading&#39;, &#39;lazy&#39;);
        wrapper.innerHTML = &#39;&#39;;
        wrapper.appendChild(iframe);
      });
    });
  });
&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;In a discussion led by Jordan Peterson and Dr. Benjamin Bikman, a professor of Cell Biology, the conversation centers on the impact of carbohydrate intake on health, particularly regarding insulin resistance and chronic diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Key Points:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cravings and Diet&lt;/strong&gt;: The discussion begins by acknowledging the common cravings for sweet, carbohydrate-rich foods and how modern diets can spike insulin levels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insulin Resistance&lt;/strong&gt;: Dr. Bikman explains that insulin resistance, primarily caused by excessive carbohydrate consumption, leads to numerous health issues, including type 2 diabetes, heart disease, and depression. He emphasizes that many chronic conditions can be traced back to high carbohydrate intake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Metabolic Health Crisis&lt;/strong&gt;: The conversation highlights the &amp;ldquo;cardiometabolic crisis&amp;rdquo; in the U.S., where a significant portion of the adult population shows signs of metabolic syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Obesity and Insulin Resistance&lt;/strong&gt;: The relationship between obesity and insulin resistance is explored, noting that larger fat cells become resistant to insulin, exacerbating metabolic issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dietary Recommendations&lt;/strong&gt;: Dr. Bikman advocates for reducing carbohydrate intake and adopting low-carb or ketogenic diets to improve metabolic health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critique of Dietary Guidelines&lt;/strong&gt;: The discussion criticizes government dietary guidelines, particularly the food pyramid, for promoting excessive carbohydrate consumption while neglecting fats and proteins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insulin’s Role in Disease&lt;/strong&gt;: They discuss how chronically high insulin levels lead to various diseases, including Alzheimer’s and cancer, and argue for a shift in treatment focus from glucose to insulin management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Importance of Dietary Fats&lt;/strong&gt;: Contrary to mainstream beliefs, fats are highlighted as crucial for metabolic health and hormonal balance, with evidence linking meat consumption to better reproductive health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Government Policy Impact&lt;/strong&gt;: The conversation touches on how government subsidies promote unhealthy eating habits through inexpensive, carbohydrate-rich foods, calling for a public health approach that emphasizes personal responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall Health Improvement&lt;/strong&gt;: The hosts conclude that individuals can significantly enhance their health by modifying their diets, primarily by reducing carbohydrate intake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notable Insights:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dr. Bikman asserts there is no essential carbohydrate, stating the brain can switch to using ketones for energy as soon as they are available, even when glucose is present. He argues that this contradicts mainstream medical consensus that prioritizes glucose as the primary fuel source for brain function.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In the discussion, a significant point emerged regarding human metabolic pathways and their implications for health and longevity. Dr. Bikman articulated that humans possess two primary metabolic pathways, with the carbohydrate pathway being a relatively recent adaptation primarily used in emergencies. This pathway provides a quick source of energy but is limited in supply. When carbohydrates are depleted-such as during a 24-hour fast-the body transitions into a state of ketogenesis, utilizing fat for energy. This shift is crucial, particularly when considering the challenges faced by our ancestors during times of food scarcity, which likely triggered the activation of autophagy, a process where the body digests its own damaged tissues. This mechanism allows for regeneration and repair, enabling survival during difficult periods. Dr. Bikman emphasized that a constant reliance on carbohydrates prevents the body from entering an autophagic state, potentially hindering its ability to repair and rejuvenate itself. He proposed that a carnivore diet may not only mimic the effects of autophagy but actively promote it, which could explain its effectiveness for some individuals. Additionally, the discussion touched on the intricate balance between growth and decay in cellular processes, highlighting the role of hormones in determining whether cells are in a building or breaking phase. Dr. Bikman noted that optimizing the process of cellular death through autophagy is essential for long-term health, suggesting that a carnivore diet may facilitate this balance by reducing reliance on an emergency food supply that often leads to fat accumulation. The conversation also hinted at the broader implications of insulin resistance, a condition exacerbated by chronic high carbohydrate intake. Dr. Bikman encouraged a deeper exploration of the mechanisms behind insulin resistance and its connections to a range of health issues, including diabetes, obesity, and various age-related diseases, underscoring the importance of understanding these metabolic pathways for improving overall health and longevity.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The discussion serves as a call to action for individuals to reassess their dietary habits, particularly regarding carbohydrate consumption, to combat the growing health crises in modern society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;video-wrapper&#34; data-video-id=&#34;NyFSkGMWP5Q&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img 
    src=&#34;https://img.youtube.com/vi/NyFSkGMWP5Q/hqdefault.jpg&#34; 
    alt=&#34;Video Thumbnail&#34; 
    loading=&#34;lazy&#34; 
    class=&#34;video-thumbnail&#34; 
  /&gt;
  &lt;button class=&#34;play-button&#34; aria-label=&#34;Play&#34;&gt;
    
    
    
    &lt;svg width=&#34;40&#34; height=&#34;40&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 24 24&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34; xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34;&gt;
      &lt;circle cx=&#34;12&#34; cy=&#34;12&#34; r=&#34;10&#34; fill=&#34;rgba(0,0,0,0.6)&#34; /&gt;
      &lt;polygon points=&#34;10,8 16,12 10,16&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/svg&gt;
  &lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  document.addEventListener(&#39;DOMContentLoaded&#39;, () =&gt; {
    document.querySelectorAll(&#39;.video-wrapper&#39;).forEach(wrapper =&gt; {
      wrapper.querySelector(&#39;.play-button&#39;).addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, () =&gt; {
        const videoId = wrapper.dataset.videoId;
        const iframe = document.createElement(&#39;iframe&#39;);
        iframe.src = `https://www.youtube.com/embed/${videoId}?autoplay=1`;
        iframe.width = &#34;560&#34;;
        iframe.height = &#34;315&#34;;
        iframe.allowFullscreen = true;
        iframe.setAttribute(&#39;loading&#39;, &#39;lazy&#39;);
        wrapper.innerHTML = &#39;&#39;;
        wrapper.appendChild(iframe);
      });
    });
  });
&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://stevenbartlett.com/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/DOAC-Benjamin-Bikman-independent-research.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;podcast&lt;/a&gt; featuring Dr. Benjamin Bikman delves into various aspects of insulin resistance and its implications for health. Here’s a summary of the key topics discussed:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insulin Resistance and Health Problems&lt;/strong&gt;: Insulin resistance is identified as a common underlying factor in several serious health conditions, including Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s disease, type 2 diabetes, and cardiovascular diseases. The relationship between insulin function and brain activity suggests that targeting insulin resistance may offer potential treatments for Alzheimer&amp;rsquo;s.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adipose Tissue and Type 2 Diabetes&lt;/strong&gt;: The growth of fat tissue, particularly visceral fat, is linked to an increased risk of type 2 diabetes through mechanisms involving inflammation and insulin resistance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inflammation and Insulin Resistance&lt;/strong&gt;: Inflammation resulting from enlarged fat cells contributes significantly to insulin resistance. The size and function of fat cells are critical determinants of metabolic health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Insulin Resistance and Other Conditions&lt;/strong&gt;: The podcast discusses the connections between insulin resistance and hypertension, erectile dysfunction, and polycystic ovary syndrome (PCOS), highlighting how insulin impacts reproductive health and blood pressure regulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ethnic Differences&lt;/strong&gt;: There are notable ethnic variations in fat storage and predisposition to metabolic disorders, influencing how different populations experience insulin resistance and related health issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dietary Factors&lt;/strong&gt;: The impact of carbohydrate consumption and meal frequency on insulin levels is examined, with discussions on how meal composition influences insulin response.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ketones and Metabolism&lt;/strong&gt;: Ketone bodies are presented as an alternative energy source for the brain, especially when glucose metabolism is impaired. The discussion includes the potential cognitive benefits of ketogenic diets, particularly for individuals with metabolic disorders or cognitive decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Longevity and Lifestyle Factors&lt;/strong&gt;: The podcast touches on various lifestyle factors that influence longevity, including diet, exercise, and social connections. Loneliness is noted as a significant risk factor for mortality, potentially surpassing even smoking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cholesterol and Hormones&lt;/strong&gt;: The relationship between cholesterol levels, sex hormones, and insulin resistance is highlighted, emphasizing the complexities of metabolic health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Environmental Influences&lt;/strong&gt;: Factors such as smoking, air pollution, and exposure to toxins like diesel exhaust are discussed regarding their role in exacerbating insulin resistance and related health issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Health Interventions&lt;/strong&gt;: The podcast concludes with insights into potential health interventions, including dietary changes, exercise, and medical treatments, for managing insulin resistance and improving overall metabolic health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the discussion, Dr. Bikman emphasizes the interconnectedness of metabolic health, the importance of understanding individual risk factors, and the need for a multidisciplinary approach to treatment and prevention. The information shared is for educational purposes and should not replace professional medical advice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/@benbikman&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Ben Bikman&amp;rsquo;s YouTube Channel&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;video-wrapper&#34; data-video-id=&#34;lZZCLlX05PQ&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img 
    src=&#34;https://img.youtube.com/vi/lZZCLlX05PQ/hqdefault.jpg&#34; 
    alt=&#34;Video Thumbnail&#34; 
    loading=&#34;lazy&#34; 
    class=&#34;video-thumbnail&#34; 
  /&gt;
  &lt;button class=&#34;play-button&#34; aria-label=&#34;Play&#34;&gt;
    
    
    
    &lt;svg width=&#34;40&#34; height=&#34;40&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 24 24&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34; xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34;&gt;
      &lt;circle cx=&#34;12&#34; cy=&#34;12&#34; r=&#34;10&#34; fill=&#34;rgba(0,0,0,0.6)&#34; /&gt;
      &lt;polygon points=&#34;10,8 16,12 10,16&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/svg&gt;
  &lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  document.addEventListener(&#39;DOMContentLoaded&#39;, () =&gt; {
    document.querySelectorAll(&#39;.video-wrapper&#39;).forEach(wrapper =&gt; {
      wrapper.querySelector(&#39;.play-button&#39;).addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, () =&gt; {
        const videoId = wrapper.dataset.videoId;
        const iframe = document.createElement(&#39;iframe&#39;);
        iframe.src = `https://www.youtube.com/embed/${videoId}?autoplay=1`;
        iframe.width = &#34;560&#34;;
        iframe.height = &#34;315&#34;;
        iframe.allowFullscreen = true;
        iframe.setAttribute(&#39;loading&#39;, &#39;lazy&#39;);
        wrapper.innerHTML = &#39;&#39;;
        wrapper.appendChild(iframe);
      });
    });
  });
&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;div class=&#34;video-wrapper&#34; data-video-id=&#34;VaVC3PAWqLk&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img 
    src=&#34;https://img.youtube.com/vi/VaVC3PAWqLk/hqdefault.jpg&#34; 
    alt=&#34;Video Thumbnail&#34; 
    loading=&#34;lazy&#34; 
    class=&#34;video-thumbnail&#34; 
  /&gt;
  &lt;button class=&#34;play-button&#34; aria-label=&#34;Play&#34;&gt;
    
    
    
    &lt;svg width=&#34;40&#34; height=&#34;40&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 24 24&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34; xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34;&gt;
      &lt;circle cx=&#34;12&#34; cy=&#34;12&#34; r=&#34;10&#34; fill=&#34;rgba(0,0,0,0.6)&#34; /&gt;
      &lt;polygon points=&#34;10,8 16,12 10,16&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/svg&gt;
  &lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  document.addEventListener(&#39;DOMContentLoaded&#39;, () =&gt; {
    document.querySelectorAll(&#39;.video-wrapper&#39;).forEach(wrapper =&gt; {
      wrapper.querySelector(&#39;.play-button&#39;).addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, () =&gt; {
        const videoId = wrapper.dataset.videoId;
        const iframe = document.createElement(&#39;iframe&#39;);
        iframe.src = `https://www.youtube.com/embed/${videoId}?autoplay=1`;
        iframe.width = &#34;560&#34;;
        iframe.height = &#34;315&#34;;
        iframe.allowFullscreen = true;
        iframe.setAttribute(&#39;loading&#39;, &#39;lazy&#39;);
        wrapper.innerHTML = &#39;&#39;;
        wrapper.appendChild(iframe);
      });
    });
  });
&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Dr. Thomas Seyfried mentions at the beginning of the podcast a troubling trend: cancer is experiencing exponential growth in the American population. This trend is also evident in many other nations around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even without delving into debates about biochemistry, it is clear that despite all efforts to contain and treat cancer, these efforts are far from sufficient. More and more people are developing various types of cancer worldwide. Lifestyle and nutritional factors must be considered to prevent cancer effectively. Therefore, it would be logical to direct more research efforts toward this area rather than focusing solely on managing the problem, which is obviously getting out of hand. Identifying the causes and finding ways to prevent cancer extend beyond the scope of traditional medicine. Environmental factors-such as food, toxic substances, and lifestyle-must also be taken into account. Finding the root cause and addressing it is much easier than attempting to unravel the Gordian knot presented by the current situation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a thought-provoking excerpt from the interview in transcript form:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steven Bartlett:&lt;/strong&gt;
Are you hopeful?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr Thomas Seyfried:&lt;/strong&gt;
I am very hopeful because people, when the science comes you can&amp;rsquo;t suppress the truth. It&amp;rsquo;s going to come out. The evidence the scientific evidence is there. I&amp;rsquo;m documenting this scientific and it&amp;rsquo;s based on the shoulders of Otto Warburg are you kidding me I mean he was a giant in the field of biochemistry it&amp;rsquo;s not like I made this stuff up I&amp;rsquo;m just extending what he has done to a new dimension and putting it into a practical application which he had never done so it&amp;rsquo;s just an extension of the knowledge base over this time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steven Bartlett:&lt;/strong&gt;
Why do you care so much?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr Thomas Seyfried:&lt;/strong&gt;
Why do I care so much? You know I&amp;rsquo;m not in it for the money. You know what I&amp;rsquo;m in it for? I want to see the scientific principles substantiated. If you know that you can keep these people alive at a higher quality of life based on the knowledge of the science that&amp;rsquo;s doing that, that&amp;rsquo;s gratification man! It&amp;rsquo;s gratification to know that these&amp;hellip; if, because you arise on understanding the mechanism of the problem and if you say you know if we do it the way we&amp;rsquo;re writing a big treatment protocol as we speak it&amp;rsquo;s a really comprehensive treatment protocol and we institute that in the clinic and for glioblastoma patients and these advanced cancers they&amp;rsquo;re not living a few extra months they&amp;rsquo;re living several years longer! Why? Because you knew the science! What&amp;rsquo;s wrong with that? That&amp;rsquo;s gratification! You don&amp;rsquo;t have to make a billion dollars on that. All you have to know is that all those folks are living longer because you understood the science that was put into practical application.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our research is supported by philanthropy and private foundations. That money allows me to do these experiments, to test what I&amp;rsquo;m testing on pre-clinical models and then we translate it back into the clinic directly and we see like &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=WnWPCS5qnVo&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Pablo Kelly&lt;/a&gt; he should have been done, he should have been done years and years ago, he lived all those years extra he&amp;rsquo;s had a wife and he&amp;rsquo;s got kids he didn&amp;rsquo;t have to have his sperm frozen he didn&amp;rsquo;t have to have any of that stuff done. What&amp;rsquo;s wrong with that? I&amp;rsquo;m seeing people that should have been dead a long time ago and they&amp;rsquo;re still alive and they&amp;rsquo;re saying I&amp;rsquo;m doing fine. I get calls from people, geez I thought that guy would have been a goner, he&amp;rsquo;s still alive he&amp;rsquo;s doing well. I said that keeps me going because it tells me that we&amp;rsquo;re on the right path. This is a solvable problem! This cancer can be dropped significantly. You can take away the fear. People now put it on their shoulders: I know what to do how to do it: I&amp;rsquo;m going to follow this. Will it work for everybody? No! Well it will help a lot of people much more than what we have today. But it&amp;rsquo;s paradigm change massive paradigm change so they will come to know. It&amp;rsquo;s just a matter of time, I don&amp;rsquo;t know how long it&amp;rsquo;s going to take, but I ain&amp;rsquo;t going anywhere! I&amp;rsquo;m continuing to do this. I&amp;rsquo;m going to get better and better results and we&amp;rsquo;re going to keep pushing. I published these case reports in the scientific literature. Let the scientific field make their decision on the results from these papers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steven Bartlett:&lt;/strong&gt;
And if you are to succeed what happens?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr Thomas Seyfried:&lt;/strong&gt;
People improve. Um, what&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m not going to live forever, so&amp;hellip; But I know that what I&amp;rsquo;ve done with following Otto Warburg and cleaning up the misconceptions and misunderstanding of why he was stalled when the field ran off chasing genes. We got to bring it back on track. It&amp;rsquo;s a metabolic problem with metabolic solutions. So that will help a lot of people. But it&amp;rsquo;s also going to change a lot of way people are thinking about this but I can tell you they want to open clinics. I get calls from Asia, Africa, South America, they want to open clinics. People are being brutalized by a system that&amp;rsquo;s not working. Don&amp;rsquo;t forget besides the terrible financial toxicity, the personal physical toxicity people have gone bankrupt their marriages are falling apart because they can&amp;rsquo;t pay for the expensive drugs on these cancer things and they die and the bills are passed on to their loved ones. This is immoral stuff!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steven Bartlett:&lt;/strong&gt;
Is there a particular case thats broken your heart more than any others?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr Thomas Seyfried:&lt;/strong&gt;
Trudy Dupont who originally let me&amp;hellip; we, we&amp;rsquo;ve&amp;rsquo; built a glucose ketone index calculator on her. Pablo is&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m still&amp;hellip; We&amp;rsquo;re still devastated by Pablo&amp;rsquo;s loss, because Pablo was a guy that I&amp;rsquo;ve known for 10 years! Worked him through and then all of a sudden he gets a cerebral hemorrhage and dies. He was our poster child for how long you could live with a glioblastoma on metabolic therapy but he didn&amp;rsquo;t die from the cancer. Um yeah, have there&amp;rsquo;s some others that we wished they could have lived a little bit longer with the appropriate help. What I find is that sometimes within the family there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of&amp;hellip; The guy! He&amp;rsquo;s: I really want to do what you&amp;rsquo;re doing but my wife and kids saying I&amp;rsquo;m foolish to do that. So it&amp;rsquo;s still a very&amp;hellip; we&amp;rsquo;re in a very early stage of this. We haven&amp;rsquo;t really worked it out into an effective standard yet. It will come, so people&amp;hellip; And the other members of the family get super help when they all work together and they do it&amp;hellip; Everybody says: I never felt so healthy in my life! Um Guy Tannenbaum had advanced prostate cancer, he wrote a book and he&amp;rsquo;s on the web and he had hypertension high blood pressure overweight more obesity and all everything and then he does several 18-day water only fasts got himself&amp;hellip; Everything all these things went away his diabetes went away his hypertension high blood pressure and the cancer can&amp;rsquo;t be found. So is he cured? I have no idea. But he&amp;rsquo;s managed? Yes, he&amp;rsquo;s managed and he&amp;rsquo;s healthier. So what&amp;rsquo;s wrong with that? Isn&amp;rsquo;t that ultimately what medicine wants to do? Keep people alive longer and a healthier quality of life? Yeah! How many more do we need? They say oh that&amp;rsquo;s a fluke, that&amp;rsquo;s a fluke, that&amp;rsquo;s a fluke, that&amp;rsquo;s a fluke! (showing wildly around) How many damn flukes do you want?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steven Bartlett:&lt;/strong&gt;
If there&amp;rsquo;s someone listening now. And I&amp;rsquo;m sure there&amp;rsquo;s going to be many thousands and tens of thousands of people listening, um, that are currently battling cancer, have early stage diagnosis&amp;hellip;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr Thomas Seyfried:&lt;/strong&gt;
I know. I feel bad about this because people say oh I want to do metabolic therapy where can I go? And they go to their local hospital and get slapped out. There&amp;rsquo;s no evidence there&amp;rsquo;s&amp;hellip; everything that&amp;rsquo;s should come out of my mouth has never been taught to me in medical school.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Steven Bartlett:&lt;/strong&gt;
So what do you say to those people?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dr Thomas Seyfried:&lt;/strong&gt;
You know, I say&amp;hellip; I&amp;rsquo;m sorry that the medical establishment has not come to recognize what I&amp;rsquo;m saying. And then I tell them&amp;hellip; yes, right the change has to be coming from the people, it ain’t going to come from the top medical schools. They are doing what they&amp;rsquo;re doing. Very.. the status quo is very profitable, the status quo is very effective for these people but it&amp;rsquo;s not helping the cancer patient as well as it can. And don&amp;rsquo;t forget we&amp;rsquo;re not throwing out all this stuff we&amp;rsquo;re just asking people to know how to use the tools we have in a better way! We don&amp;rsquo;t have to throw out immunotherapies, radiation, we don&amp;rsquo;t have to throw out toxic poisons. We just have to know better how to use it when the patient is in this new state. And the data will prove it. But who&amp;rsquo;s going to do that??? Who is going to do that? The doctor says I&amp;rsquo;d love to do this if I,.. but I&amp;rsquo;m going to lose my license if I do it. What&amp;rsquo;s going on with that?!? They wrote the standard of care as if it were in granite can&amp;rsquo;t be changed. No! It should be flexible. When new evidence comes:&amp;hellip; I don&amp;rsquo;t believe your evidence! What number do you not believe, what piece of science do you not believe on this??? &amp;ldquo;Well I haven&amp;rsquo;t read it.&amp;rdquo; You can&amp;rsquo;t be right when 99% of the world says it&amp;rsquo;s this way and you&amp;rsquo;re saying it&amp;rsquo;s something different, that&amp;rsquo;s confirmation bias.  You&amp;rsquo;re not looking at the numbers! And then when they get cancer they come:.. Hey! What can you do for me? You know it&amp;rsquo;s like,.. it&amp;rsquo;s like that.. But yes, it has to change, it will change, because we&amp;rsquo;re on the momentum to move it. People are coming to know this and once the change happens it&amp;rsquo;s going to be like a major change and people are going to have to just readjust.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I genuinely admire the attitudes and intentions of all the individuals featured in the videos above, especially Dr. Seyfried! His perspective is intriguing, and while time, history, and science will ultimately reveal the truth, he seems to be onto something significant. From my own experiences with the ketogenic lifestyle, I can say it has worked well for me-though thankfully, I haven’t had to confront cancer. I understand that everyone’s experiences may be different, but the journey of learning about how our bodies work is not only helpful; it’s also an enjoyable experience. I really appreciate it! My hope is that this information can be useful to you as well!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; The information presented in this blog is intended for educational purposes only and should not be construed as medical or nutritional advice. I am not a licensed healthcare professional, and the insights shared are based on personal experiences and research. Therefore, I cannot take responsibility for the content published, even though I have made every effort to provide factual information based on my studies of health-related topics and the findings of qualified professionals. Individual health conditions vary, and what works for one person may not be suitable for another. Always seek the guidance of a qualified healthcare provider for any medical concerns or treatment options. The perspectives shared here are meant to encourage informed discussions about health; however, they should not replace professional medical advice.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
