<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Autophagy | Hunor Becsi&#39;s Website</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/en/tags/autophagy/</link>
      <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/en/tags/autophagy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Autophagy</description>
    <generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>http://localhost:1313/media/icon_hu7729264130191091259.png</url>
      <title>Autophagy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/tags/autophagy/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unlocking Fat Loss and Healing: Dr. Mindy Pelz&#39;s Guide to Autophagy and 6 Superfoods to support it</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/en/post/autophagy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/en/post/autophagy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;these-6-foods-will-burn-fat-and-heal-body--dr-mindy-pelz-top-fasting-expert&#34;&gt;These 6 Foods will Burn Fat and Heal Body | Dr. Mindy Pelz, Top Fasting Expert&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Introduction&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently came across this video from Dr. Mindy Pelz, who is an incredible source of insight, regarding our wellbeing and health.
&lt;div class=&#34;video-wrapper&#34; data-video-id=&#34;s2ssYtWT5bY&#34;&gt;
  &lt;img 
    src=&#34;https://img.youtube.com/vi/s2ssYtWT5bY/hqdefault.jpg&#34; 
    alt=&#34;Video Thumbnail&#34; 
    loading=&#34;lazy&#34; 
    class=&#34;video-thumbnail&#34; 
  /&gt;
  &lt;button class=&#34;play-button&#34; aria-label=&#34;Play&#34;&gt;
    
    
    
    &lt;svg width=&#34;40&#34; height=&#34;40&#34; viewBox=&#34;0 0 24 24&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34; xmlns=&#34;http://www.w3.org/2000/svg&#34;&gt;
      &lt;circle cx=&#34;12&#34; cy=&#34;12&#34; r=&#34;10&#34; fill=&#34;rgba(0,0,0,0.6)&#34; /&gt;
      &lt;polygon points=&#34;10,8 16,12 10,16&#34; fill=&#34;white&#34;/&gt;
    &lt;/svg&gt;
  &lt;/button&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;script&gt;
  document.addEventListener(&#39;DOMContentLoaded&#39;, () =&gt; {
    document.querySelectorAll(&#39;.video-wrapper&#39;).forEach(wrapper =&gt; {
      wrapper.querySelector(&#39;.play-button&#39;).addEventListener(&#39;click&#39;, () =&gt; {
        const videoId = wrapper.dataset.videoId;
        const iframe = document.createElement(&#39;iframe&#39;);
        iframe.src = `https://www.youtube.com/embed/${videoId}?autoplay=1`;
        iframe.width = &#34;560&#34;;
        iframe.height = &#34;315&#34;;
        iframe.allowFullscreen = true;
        iframe.setAttribute(&#39;loading&#39;, &#39;lazy&#39;);
        wrapper.innerHTML = &#39;&#39;;
        wrapper.appendChild(iframe);
      });
    });
  });
&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&#34;why-use-autophagy-and-fasting-the-goal-is-not-merely-fasting-alone-rather-it-is-to-trigger-autophagy-through-fasting&#34;&gt;Why use autophagy and fasting? The goal is not merely fasting alone; rather, it is to trigger autophagy through fasting.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fasting and reaching autophagy can offer a variety of benefits from both health and economic perspectives. Here are some of the key advantages:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;health-benefits&#34;&gt;Health Benefits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cellular Repair and Regeneration&lt;/strong&gt;: Autophagy helps remove damaged cells and proteins, promoting cellular health and longevity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weight Management&lt;/strong&gt;: Fasting can aid in weight loss and fat burning, reducing obesity-related health issues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improved Metabolic Health&lt;/strong&gt;: Fasting can enhance insulin sensitivity, lower blood sugar levels, and improve overall metabolic function.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduced Inflammation&lt;/strong&gt;: Fasting has been shown to decrease markers of inflammation, which is linked to various chronic diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enhanced Mental Clarity&lt;/strong&gt;: Some people report improved focus and mental clarity during fasting periods, possibly due to increased production of brain-derived neurotrophic factor (BDNF).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Potential Longevity Benefits&lt;/strong&gt;: Studies suggest that fasting and autophagy may contribute to increased lifespan by promoting cellular repair and reducing age-related diseases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Improved Heart Health&lt;/strong&gt;: Fasting can help reduce cholesterol levels and blood pressure, leading to better cardiovascular health.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Boosted Immune Function&lt;/strong&gt;: Fasting may enhance immune response and promote the regeneration of immune cells.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;economic-benefits&#34;&gt;Economic Benefits&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reduced Food Costs&lt;/strong&gt;: Fasting reduces the number of meals you need to purchase, which can lead to significant savings on grocery bills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lower Healthcare Costs&lt;/strong&gt;: By improving health metrics and reducing the risk of chronic diseases, fasting can lead to lower medical expenses over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Increased Productivity&lt;/strong&gt;: Enhanced mental clarity and energy from fasting can improve work performance, potentially leading to better job outcomes and income.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time Savings&lt;/strong&gt;: Fasting simplifies meal planning and preparation, freeing up time that can be spent on other productive activities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Less Dependency on Supplements&lt;/strong&gt;: The health benefits associated with fasting may reduce the need for dietary supplements, leading to additional financial savings.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lowered Eating Out Costs&lt;/strong&gt;: With fewer meals to prepare or purchase, there&amp;rsquo;s a potential decrease in spending on dining out or takeout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Simplicity in Diet Choices&lt;/strong&gt;: Fasting can simplify dietary choices, reducing the time and money spent on selecting various foods and products.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;conclusion&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fasting and reaching autophagy can provide numerous health benefits while also being economically advantageous. By promoting better health, reducing food costs, and increasing productivity, fasting offers a compelling case for individuals looking to improve their overall well-being while managing their finances effectively. However, it&amp;rsquo;s important to consult with a healthcare professional before starting any fasting regimen, especially for those with existing health conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;heres-a-text-summary-of-the-video-i-wanted-to-share-with-you-just-because-it-is-so-important-and-many-people-simply-do-not-know-about-this&#34;&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s a text summary of the video I wanted to share with you, just because it is so important and many people simply do not know about this:&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You have the power to heal yourself without relying on money or time. We can end chronic disease, strengthen immunity, and achieve metabolic fitness for the first time. This is our path out of chronic illness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meet &lt;strong&gt;Dr. Mindy Pelz&lt;/strong&gt;, a top nutrition and functional health expert and best-selling author. She is a recognized leader in the Alternative Health field and a pioneer in the fasting movement. In this video, we distill the essence of her teachings and highlight the top six foods she consumes to promote effective autophagy, seamlessly fitting within her fasting regimen.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;the-concept-of-self-healing&#34;&gt;The Concept of Self-Healing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, nobody cures you; you cure yourself. It’s essential to view the human body as a self-healing organism, constantly figuring out how to keep you alive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-autophagy&#34;&gt;What is Autophagy?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let’s understand what autophagy is. Autophagy occurs when cells recognize that nutrients and blood sugar (glucose) are not entering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Internal Mechanism&lt;/strong&gt;: The cell assesses its situation and thinks, &amp;ldquo;Huh, nothing&amp;rsquo;s coming in? We need to improve ourselves.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Elimination of Harmful Cells&lt;/strong&gt;: It pushes out viruses and bacteria. If a cell is becoming cancerous or aging rapidly (often referred to as a &amp;ldquo;zombie cell&amp;rdquo;), it identifies that cell as a liability and eliminates it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;flex justify-center	&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/en/post/autophagy/virus.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Alt text&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Autophagy is a natural cellular process in which cells degrade and recycle their own components. The term comes from Greek words: “Auto” (self) and “Phagy” (eating). Essentially, autophagy is the body’s method of cleaning out damaged cells to regenerate newer, healthier ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For autophagy to take place, the body must be in a &lt;strong&gt;fasted state&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-is-a-fasted-state&#34;&gt;What is a Fasted State?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fasted state occurs when blood sugar levels drop sufficiently, triggering a metabolic switch from glucose metabolism to ketogenic (fat-burning) metabolism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Timing and Effects&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;8 Hours&lt;/strong&gt;: The body begins to make the switch.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;12 Hours&lt;/strong&gt;: Ketone production starts, leading to mental clarity. Hunger hormones are turned off.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;13 Hours&lt;/strong&gt;: Growth hormone levels rise, slowing the aging process and helping burn fat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;15 Hours&lt;/strong&gt;: Significant testosterone increase (up to 1300% in men) and decreasing inflammation markers (CRP).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;17 Hours&lt;/strong&gt;: Autophagy is stimulated, repairing cells and eliminating aging ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;24 Hours&lt;/strong&gt;: The gut resets, and intestinal stem cells repair the gut lining.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;36 Hours&lt;/strong&gt;: The body starts burning stubborn belly fat for energy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;48 Hours&lt;/strong&gt;: New dopamine receptor sites are created to motivate the search for food.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;72 Hours&lt;/strong&gt;: The immune system reboots itself.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process occurs naturally, without the need for drugs or supplements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;how-can-i-do-fasting&#34;&gt;How Can I Do Fasting?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should you fast for 72 hours regularly? The answer is no. Here are some guidelines:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3-Day Water Fast&lt;/strong&gt;: Twice a year to eliminate rogue cells potentially leading to tumors.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;48-Hour Fast&lt;/strong&gt;: Once a quarter, beneficial for mental health challenges like depression and anxiety.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;36-Hour Fast&lt;/strong&gt;: Once a month for those struggling with weight loss.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;24-Hour Fast&lt;/strong&gt;: Once a week can be miraculous; this is often referred to as &amp;ldquo;one meal a day.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most people should typically fast between 12 to 17 hours regularly, except women during the week before their menstrual cycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When fasting, it’s crucial to be mindful of food choices. Here are the &lt;strong&gt;top six foods&lt;/strong&gt; that Dr. Mindy frequently consumes to maximize the benefits of fasting:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;top-six-foods-to-maximize-fasting-benefits&#34;&gt;Top Six Foods to Maximize Fasting Benefits&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Avocado&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great for breaking a fast.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Breaking a fast with fat kills the hunger hormone and reduces subsequent cravings.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Often paired with probiotic foods like sauerkraut and kimchi for added benefits.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cacao&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A source of chocolate that stimulates autophagy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Look for clean cacao sources, with the first ingredient being cacao and the second ingredient cacao butter.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dark chocolate is preferable for higher cacao content.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coffee&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Increases autophagy in liver, muscle, and heart tissue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Choose organic, mold-free coffee.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Black coffee is generally acceptable during fasting; adding MCT oil may enhance fat-burning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Green Tea&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A great alternative to coffee for those seeking less stimulation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stimulates autophagy in various cells.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bergamot tea has also been shown to induce autophagy in cancer cells.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Olive Oil&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensure it’s organic and not rancid.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Avoid heating, as it can turn into an inflammatory fat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Has beneficial effects on Alzheimer’s-related proteins and cancer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Curcumin&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The active component in turmeric.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can be consumed in various forms, such as sprinkled on food or juiced.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research indicates it increases autophagy and inhibits disease proliferation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion-1&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Dr. Mindy Pelz, it’s essential to establish a long-term strategy to stimulate autophagy. If you neglect this, your cells will accumulate toxins, hindering your health. Embrace this knowledge and start your journey toward self-healing today!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Disclaimer:&lt;/strong&gt; The information provided here is for educational and informational purposes only and should not be considered medical or nutritional advice. I am not a doctor or a licensed healthcare professional, and I am not a nutritionist. Therefore, I cannot take responsibility for the content published, even though I have made every effort to provide factual information based on my studies of health-related topics and the findings of qualified professionals. Always consult with a qualified healthcare provider for any medical concerns, treatment options, or questions regarding your health. Relying solely on this information may not be appropriate for your individual circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
